Guide to the Human Rights Watch Records: Helsinki Watch,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Human Rights Watch Records: Helsinki Watch,
1952-2003
[Bulk Dates: 1978-1994].
Human Rights Watch/Helsinki (Organization: U.S.)
271 linear feet (645 document boxes and one flat box).
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library, New York, NY. 10027
6062290
This collection contains the records of the United States based human rights organization, Human Rights Watch. Materials include correspondence and e-mail communications, professional and personal field notes, testimonies and interviews, advocacy, policy planning material, and briefing papers.
History
In 1978, under the direction of founder and former chair Robert L. Bernstein, Human Rights Watch (HRW) was established as Helsinki Watch (HW). HW's mission was to monitor the compliance of the former Soviet Union and some other signatories with the human rights provisions of the 1975 Helsinki Final Act.
As the organization has grown, it has formed other watch committees to cover other regions of the world. In 1988, all of the committees were united under one organization to form Human Rights Watch. These watch committees -- now called regional divisions --produce research reports on violations of international human rights norms as set out by the Universal Declaration of Human Rights and other internationally-accepted human rights norms. These reports are intended to draw international attention to human rights abuses and to put pressure on governments and international organizations to reform. HRW researchers conduct fact-finding missions to investigate suspect situations and generate coverage in local and international media. Issues raised by HRW include social and gender discrimination, torture, military use of children, political corruption, and abuses in criminal justice systems, and violations of humanitarian and international law.
In the ensuing years, besides issuing reports, HRW has also expanded its collaborative lobbying efforts to expose human rights abuses throughout the world. Human Rights Watch, for example, was one of six international NGOs that established the Coalition to Stop the Use of Child Soldiers in 1998. In turn, it is also the co-chair of the International Campaign to Ban Landmines, a global coalition of civil society groups that have successfully lobbied to introduce the Ottawa Convention, a treaty that prohibits the use of anti-personnel landmines. Finally, HRW is an original member of the International Freedom of Expression Exchange, a global network of non-governmental organizations that monitor censorship worldwide. Each year, in turn, Human Rights Watch awards grants to writers worldwide who are in financial need and are victims of persecution. These Hellman/Hammett grants are financed by the estate of the playwright Lillian Hellman with funds established in her name and that of her long-time companion, the novelist Dashiell Hammett. In addition to providing financial assistance, the Hellman/Hammett grants attempt to raise awareness of censorship.
Today, HRW remains the largest U.S. based human rights organization “dedicated to protecting the human rights of people around the world.” With more than 150 committed professionals, a growing number of devoted volunteers working in its five regional and almost two dozen thematic divisions and through special projects orchestrated from its New York and Washington D.C. offices, HRW tracks human rights developments in over 70 countries around the world.
Scope and Content
Materials include correspondence and e-mail communications, professional and personal field notes, testimonies and interviews, material on research methodology, addresses and contact lists, confidential interoffice memos, legal and advocacy material, internal planning and policy material, declassified government and United Nations documents, published and unpublished human rights reports from individuals and fellow non-governmental organizations (NGOs), press clippings and news releases, as well as regional maps, posters and audiovisual material. Another category of documents consists of HRW reports and briefing papers, as well as press releases and open letters to heads of state, governments and various government agencies.
Materials related to missions contain unpublished information on sources, cases, and the state of affairs in various countries. They include professional and personal mission notes taken by country researchers during investigative field trips, testimonies by and interviews with victims of various human rights abuses, pre-mission and post-mission memos, material on research methodology, correspondence and e-mail communications, addresses and contact lists, as well as photographic records.
Regionally and thematically, these documents cover human rights events in the past quarter of a century. The material in the Helsinki Watch files is substantive in dissidents and opposition movements in the former Soviet Union and its satellites. The other Watches and thematic divisions contain extensive and detailed files on civil wars and conflicts in El Salvador, Guatemala, Argentina, Chile; on the Cambodian genocide, on the human rights record of Burma, China, North Korea, and Kashmir; on South Africa, Liberia, Nigeria, etc., the democratic transitions in various African countries, and the Rwandan genocide; on the Israeli-Palestinian conflict, Lebanon, Syria, Libya, Iraq; on the International Justice Program and the campaign for establishing the International Criminal Court; on the international coalition to ban land mines, ending the use of child soldiers; on women's and children's rights, campaigns to promote freedom of expression and academic freedom, and the prison project.
Record Group 7: Helsinki Watch/Europe and Central Asia (ECA), 1952-2003. This Record Group is arranged into 11 series. The Helsinki Watch files are substantive in dissidents and opposition movements in the former Soviet Union and its satellites: the Moscow Helsinki Group, the refusenik and peace movements, Charter 77, Solidarność and others. Extensive files exist on issues related to national minorities, especially the situation of Kurds in Turkey (and neighboring Iraq) and of Turks in Bulgaria. Other topics covered are the Soviet invasion of Afghanistan, psychiatric abuses against dissidents and political prisoners, the fall of the Berlin Wall and the revolutions of 1989, the disintegration of the Soviet Union and Yugoslavia, respectively, and the ethnic conflicts and wars in the Balkans. A good part of the documents reveal the fundamental role of HRW not only in establishing the United Nations tribunal for the former Yugoslavia, but also their cooperation in various criminal investigations through mutual exchange of information.
Arrangement
This Record Group is arranged into 11 series:
Series I: Jeri Laber Files, 1971-2003
Series II: Holly Cartner Files, 1952-1995
Series III: Cathy Fitzpatrick Files, 1968-1993
Series IV: Janet Fleischmann Files, 1974-1990
Series V: Ted Zang Files, 1978-1990
Series VI: Ivana Nizich Files, 1990-1995
Series VII: Chris Panico Files, 1979-1992
Series VIII: New York Office Files, 1975-1996
Series IX: Washington D.C. Office Files, 1978-1998
Series X: International Helsinki Federation for Human Rights Files, 1975-1996
Series XI: USSR/Independent States Files, 1983-1997
Subjects
Human Rights Watch (Organization); Commonwealth of Independent States--Politics and government.; CSCE Cultural Forum (1985 :--Budapest, Hungary)--lcsh.; Abkhazia (Georgia)--History--Autonomy and independence movements.; Afghanistan--History--Soviet occupation, 1979-1989.; Armenia (Republic)--History--1988-; Azerbaijan--Politics and government--1991-; Baltic States--Foreign relations.; Bulgaria--Ethnic relations.; Bulgaria--Politics and government.; Croatia--Foreign relations--1990-; Croatia--Politics and government--1990-; Czechoslovakia--Intellectual life.; Czechoslovakia--Politics and government.; Europe, Eastern--Politics and government--1989-; Former Yugoslav republics--History.; Georgia (Republic)--Foreign relations--1991-; Germany (East)--Foreign relations.; Germany (East)--Social conditions.; Hungary--Intellectual life--20th century.; Kosovo (Republic)--Relations--Albania.; Moldova--Politics and government--1991-; Romania--Foreign economic relations--United States.; South Ossetia (Georgia); Soviet Union--Ethnic relations.; Soviet Union--Intellectual life.; Soviet Union--Politics and government--1985-1991.; Soviet Union--Politics and government--1991-1997.; Turkey--Ethnic relations.; Yugoslavia--History--1980-1992.; Human rights advocacy--United States.; Human rights workers.; Jews--Migrations--Government policy--Soviet Union.; Nagorno-Karabakh Conflict, 1988-1994.
Access Restrictions
This collection is located off-site. You will need to request this material at least twenty-four (24) hours in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library Reading Room. Please consult the Rare Book and Manuscript Library for further information.
Some parts of the HRW Records are restricted. Restrictions are noted in scope and content notes and indicated in the contents list. Access to restricted material may only be granted with the written permission of HRW.
Acquisition
Human Rights Watch Deposit 2005.
The records were originally deposited at the University of Colorado at Bolder.
- Series I: Jeri Laber Files
  This series contains files relating to Jeri Laber’s work as HRW Executive Director from 1979 through 1995. Files are arranged alphabetically and contain correspondence, mission and research files.
  - Subseries I.1: Country Files
    - Afghanistan
      - General, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - Abouchar, Jacques, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - Addresses, contacts, 1984-1987 (Box 1, Folder 3)
        [restricted until 2063]
      - Afghan Information Centre: Bulletins, 1984-1987, (4 Folders) (Box 1, Folder 4-7)
      - Afghan-Pakistani peace agreement, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - Agriculture, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - Afghanistan Support Committee (UK), undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - Almqvist, Börje, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - Amnesty International: Campaign for the abolition of torture, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 1)
      - Background information, maps, 1984-1986 (Box 2, Folder 2)
      - Barry, Michael--Missions--Reports, 1982-1987 (Box 2, Folder 3)
      - Branigin, William: “Inside a Soviet War Zone”, Washington Post, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 4)
      - Children
        - General, 1985-1987 (Box 2, Folder 5)
        - Deportation of Afghan children, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 6)
          [restricted until 2061]
      - Children’s health, 1985-1986 (Box 2, Folder 7)
      - Correspondence
        - General, 1984-1988 (Box 2, Folder 8)
        - Afghan report, 1984-1985 (Box 2, Folder 9)
      - Culture, 1986-1988 (Box 2, Folder 10)
      - Dupree, Louis, 1982-1984 (Box 2, Folder 11)
      - Education--Development Center for Afghan Education Report to the International Rescue Committee, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 12)
      - Famine, Afghan Aid, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 13)
      - Geneva Conventions, undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
      - Geneva Talks, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 15)
      - Helsinki Watch Report
        - Draft 1, 1987-1988 (Box 2, Folder 16)
        - Draft 2, 1987-1988 (Box 2, Folder 17)
        - Final (1988), 1988-1989 (Box 2, Folder 18)
      - Helsinki Watch Report: Tears, Blood, and Cries
        - General, 1984-1985 (Box 3, Folder 1)
        - Press coverage, 1984-1986 (Box 3, Folder 2)
        - Response to the Report, 1984-1985 (Box 3, Folder 3)
        - Since the Report, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 4)
        - U.S. Congress, 1985-1986 (Box 3, Folder 5)
      - Helsinki Watch Reports and articles:Five Years After the Soviet Invasion, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 6)
      - Helsinki Watch Reports and articles--Responses and reactions, 1986-1988 (Box 3, Folder 7)
      - Human rights organizations, 1985-1988 (Box 3, Folder 8)
      - ICRC (International Committee of the Red Cross), 1985-1987 (Box 3, Folder 9)
      - Intellectuals, 1982-1985 (Box 3, Folder 10)
      - Interviews, testimonies, 1983-1984 (Box 3, Folder 11)
        [restricted until 2060]
      - Iranian role, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 12)
      - Islam, 1985-1987 (Box 3, Folder 13)
      - Kakar, Hasan, 1984-1988 (Box 3, Folder 14)
      - Laber: Trip to Pakistan: Follow-up, 1986-1987 (Box 3, Folder 15)
      - Laber-Rubin: “The War in the City”, New Republic, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 16)
      - Trip to Paris, Stockholm, 1984-1985 (Box 3, Folder 17)
      - Trip to Peshawar, 1984-1985 (Box 3, Folder 18)
      - Majrooh, Sayd B. and Sayd N., 1988 (Box 3, Folder 19)
      - Massacres
        - General, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 20)
        - Dara-E-Noor, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 21)
        - Russian Atrocities in Afghanistan, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 22)
      - Medical groups
        - Afghan Medical Mujahideen Medical Journal, 1986-1987 (Box 3, Folder 23)
        - Doctors Without Borders: Malhuret: Report From Afghanistan,1983-1984 (Box 3, Folder 24)
        - French doctors, 1984-1988 (Box 3, Folder 25)
      - Mercy Fund, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - Najibullah, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 2)
      - National Committee for Human Rights in Afghanistan (ANC)
        - General, 1980-1988 (Box 4, Folder 3)
        - Russia's Barbarism in Afghanistan I., 1984-1985, (2 Folders) (Box 4, Folder 4-5)
      - Official Trip (preparations), 1985-1988 (Box 4, Folder 6)
        [restricted until 2064]
      - Official Visits--United States, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 7)
      - Other Groups--working on Afghanistan, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 8)
      - Peace negotiations, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 9)
      - Permanent People’s Tribunal: Session on Afghanistan, 1981-1982 (Box 4, Folder 10)
      - Photos--Afghanistan--Downtown Magazine, 1985 (Box 4, Folder 11)
      - Polish role, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 12)
      - Polish fighters, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 13)
      - Press clippings, 1983-1986, (4 Folders) (Box 4, Folder 14-17)
      - Press clippings, 1987-1989, (3 Folders) (Box 5, Folder 1-3)
      - Prisoners of Conscience, 1983 (Box 5, Folder 4)
      - Psychiatry Center for Afghans, 1986-1987 (Box 5, Folder 5)
      - Refugee and political asylum policy, 1983-1985 (Box 5, Folder 6)
      - Refugee repatriation, 1988 (Box 5, Folder 7)
      - Refugees
        - General, 1985-1986 (Box 5, Folder 8)
        - In Iran, 1984-1987 (Box 5, Folder 9)
        - In Pakistan, 1984-1987 (Box 5, Folder 10)
        - In the U.S., 1984 (Box 5, Folder 11)
      - Reports--Human Rights Situation and War Crimes, 1986-1987 (Box 5, Folder 12)
      - Resistance: Leaders and political parties, 1985-1988 (Box 5, Folder 13)
      - Rone, Jemera
        - Report on Afghanistan, 1988 (Box 5, Folder 14)
        - Trip to Afghanistan, 1987 (Box 5, Folder 15)
      - Rubin, Barnett
        - Articles, correspondence, 1985-1988 (Box 6, Folder 1)
        - Manuscript, 1987 (Box 6, Folder 2)
        - Report outline, 1984 (Box 6, Folder 3)
        - Testimony--Congressional Task Force on Afghanistan, 1985 (Box 6, Folder 4)
      - Trip to Afghanistan, 1985 (Box 6, Folder 5)
      - Soviet Central Asia, 1986-1987 (Box 6, Folder 6)
      - Soviet defectors, 1984 (Box 6, Folder 7)
      - Soviet press coverage, 1985-1986 (Box 6, Folder 8)
      - Soviet press report, 1986-1987 (Box 6, Folder 9)
      - Soviet prisoners, 1984-1985 (Box 6, Folder 10)
      - Soviet response, 1987 (Box 6, Folder 11)
      - Soviet samizdat, 1984 (Box 6, Folder 12)
      - Soviet soldiers, 1985-1986 (Box 6, Folder 13)
      - Soviet troops, 1986 (Box 6, Folder 14)
      - Testimony form Questionnaire, undated (Box 6, Folder 15)
      - Torture
        - General, 1984-1986 (Box 6, Folder 16)
        - Women victims, 1985 (Box 6, Folder 17)
      - Toy bombs, 1986 (Box 6, Folder 18)
      - Tribal areas, undated (Box 6, Folder 19)
      - United Nations
        - General, 1984-1987 (Box 6, Folder 20)
        - Ermacora Report
          - General, 1984-1986 (Box 6, Folder 21)
          - Follow-up, 1985-1987 (Box 6, Folder 22)
          - Human Rights Committee, 1985-1985 (Box 6, Folder 23)
      - United States
        - Aid, 1985-1987 (Box 6, Folder 24)
        - Congressional Committee to Support Writers and Journalists, 1988 (Box 7, Folder 1)
        - Congressional hearings--Testimonies, 1985 (Box 7, Folder 2)
        - Government’s position, 1982-1986, (2 Folders) (Box 7, Folder 3-4)
        - Senate Foreign Relations Committee, 1984 (Box 7, Folder 5)
        - State Department Reports, 1984-1986 (Box 7, Folder 6)
        - Testimony before the House Subcommittee on Human Rights: Mongomery, James, 1987 (Box 7, Folder 7)
        - USSR role, 1985-1988 (Box 7, Folder 8)
        - Western press, 1986 (Box 7, Folder 9)
        - Writers, 1985 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Albania
      - General, 1985-1992 (Box 7, Folder 11)
      - Fanton, Jonathan:Albania: A First Glimpse, 1992 (Box 7, Folder 12)
      - Helsinki Watch: News from Albania, 1991 (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - Armenia
      - General, 1987-1988 (Box 7, Folder 14)
    - Bulgaria
      - Contacts, 1988-1991 (Box 7, Folder 15)
        [restricted until 2067]
      - General, 1983-1990, (4 Folders) (Box 7, Folder 16-19)
      - General, 1990-1994, (5 Folders) (Box 8, Folder 1-3)
      - Abortion, 1993 (Box 8, Folder 4)
      - Agça, Mehmet Ali --Bulgarian/Soviet complicity, 1982 (Box 8, Folder 5)
      - Agriculture: Law, 1991 (Box 8, Folder 6)
      - Amnesty International: Reports, 1985-1994 (Box 8, Folder 7)
        [restricted until 2070]
      - Bulgarian Diaspora, 1993 (Box 8, Folder 8)
      - Bulgarian Helsinki Committee, 1992-1994 (Box 8, Folder 9)
      - Bulgarian Turks
        - General, 1984-1987, (2 Folders) (Box 8, Folder 10-11)
        - General, 1986-1993, (2 Folders) (Box 9, Folder 1-2)
        - After the June 1986 Report--before the September 1987 Report), 1986-1987 (Box 9, Folder 3)
        - After the September 1987 Report, 1987-1988 (Box 9, Folder 4)
        - Amnesty International, 1984-1985 (Box 9, Folder 5)
        - Asylum seeker--interviewed in Istanbul, 1987 (Box 9, Folder 6)
        - Balkan Turks of America Association, 1985-1988 (Box 9, Folder 7)
        - Bulgarian Embassy press releases, 1985 (Box 9, Folder 8)
        - Congressional hearings, 1987 (Box 9, Folder 9)
        - Correspondence, 1978-1985 (Box 9, Folder 10)
        - CSCE (Conference on Security and Cooperation in Europe) Meeting of Experts on Human Rights, 1985 (Box 9, Folder 11)
        - Documents
          - Correspondence, 1971-1985 (Box 9, Folder 12)
          - Lists, photos, 1984-1985 (Box 10, Folder 1)
          - Ordinances, certificates, 1981-1985 (Box 10, Folder 2)
        - Émigré groups, 1985-1986 (Box 10, Folder 3)
        - Ethnic Turks, 1986-1987 (Box 10, Folder 4)
        - FBIS (Foreign Broadcast Information Service), 1983-1989, (2 Folders) (Box 10, Folder 5-6)
        - International support, 1985 (Box 10, Folder 7)
        - Language, 1991 (Box 10, Folder 8)
        - Letters and appeals sent to Helsinki Watch, 1986-1988 (Box 10, Folder 9)
        - Mission notes (Internal correspondence, draft report), 1985 (Box 10, Folder 10)
        - New York University Law School report (J. P. Sellers), 1987 (Box 10, Folder 11)
        - Norwegian Helsinki Committee report, 1986 (Box 10, Folder 12)
        - Political parties
          - General, 1992 (Box 11, Folder 1)
          - Movement for Rights and Freedoms (DPS), 1991-1994 (Box 11, Folder 2)
        - Press clippings, 1981-1987 (Box 11, Folder 3)
        - Property, 1992 (Box 11, Folder 4)
        - Rehabilitation, 1992 (Box 11, Folder 5)
        - Schools, 1990-1992 (Box 11, Folder 6)
        - Shestack, Jerome J.:Human Rights Abuses by Bulgaria, 1987 (Box 11, Folder 7)
        - Simsir, Bilal N.: Publications, 1986 (Box 11, Folder 8)
        - Since the June 1986 Report, 1986 (Box 11, Folder 9)
          [restricted until 2062]
        - United Nations
          - Committee on the Elimination of Racial Discrimination, 1986 (Box 11, Folder 10)
        - Statement by the Permanent Mission of Turkey, 1985 (Box 11, Folder 11)
        - Unions, 1986 (Box 11, Folder 12)
        - U.S. Government, 1985 (Box 11, Folder 13)
        - Miscellaneous, 1985-1986 (Box 11, Folder 14)
      - Bulgarians abroad, 1992 (Box 11, Folder 15)
      - Census, 1992-1993 (Box 11, Folder 16)
      - Children
        - General, 1993 (Box 11, Folder 17)
        - Adoption, 1993 (Box 11, Folder 18)
      - Chronology, 1992 (Box 11, Folder 19)
      - Computers, 1989-1990 (Box 11, Folder 20)
      - Conscription, 1992 (Box 11, Folder 21)
      - Constitution, 1991 (Box 11, Folder 22)
      - Correspondence, 1980-1985 (Box 11, Folder 23)
      - Crime: General, 1990-1993 (Box 11, Folder 24)
      - Criminal procedure and law: Drafts of the Penal Code, 1990-1993 (Box 11, Folder 25)
      - Cultural exchange, 1979-1981 (Box 11, Folder 26)
      - Death penalty, 1991-1994 (Box 11, Folder 27)
      - Decommunization, 1993 (Box 12, Folder 1)
      - Economy
        - General, 1991-1994 (Box 12, Folder 2)
        - Aid, 1991-1994 (Box 12, Folder 3)
        - Foreign investment, 1991-1992 (Box 12, Folder 4)
        - Privatization, 1991-1994 (Box 12, Folder 5)
      - Education: Open Society Fund, 1991 (Box 12, Folder 6)
      - Elections, 1994 (Box 12, Folder 7)
      - Environment, 1991-1994 (Box 12, Folder 8)
      - Film, 1993 (Box 12, Folder 9)
      - Foreign relations
        - General, 1992-1994 (Box 12, Folder 10)
        - Albania, 1994 (Box 12, Folder 11)
        - Germany, 1993-1994 (Box 12, Folder 12)
        - Greece, 1993-1994 (Box 12, Folder 13)
        - Macedonia, 1994 (Box 12, Folder 14)
        - Moldova, 1992 (Box 12, Folder 15)
        - Romania, 1993 (Box 12, Folder 16)
        - Russia, 1993 (Box 12, Folder 17)
        - United States, 1991-1995 (Box 12, Folder 18)
        - Turkey, 1992-1993 (Box 12, Folder 19)
        - Ukraine, undated (Box 12, Folder 20)
        - Yugoslavia, 1993 (Box 12, Folder 21)
      - Foreigners, 1993 (Box 12, Folder 22)
      - Free speech, 1992-1994 (Box 12, Folder 23)
      - Freedom of assembly, 1992-1993 (Box 12, Folder 24)
      - Freedom of press
        - General, 1991-1994 (Box 12, Folder 25)
        - Journalists, 1991-1994 (Box 12, Folder 26)
        - Limitations on press, 1991 (Box 12, Folder 27)
        - Prosecution of press, 1991 (Box 12, Folder 28)
        - Television, 1991-1994 (Box 12, Folder 29)
      - Freedom of religion
        - General, 1989-1994 (Box 12, Folder 30)
        - Catholics, 1990 (Box 12, Folder 31)
        - Jews, 1990-1994 (Box 12, Folder 32)
      - Freedom of travel, 1992 (Box 12, Folder 33)
      - Helsinki Watch--Press (Box 13, Folder 1)
      - History (Box 13, Folder 2)
      - Homosexuals, 1991 (Box 13, Folder 3)
      - Human Rights Committee of Bulgaria, 1990 (Box 13, Folder 4)
      - Human rights reports, 1993-1994 (Box 13, Folder 5)
      - International bodies
        - Council of Europe, 1992-1994 (Box 13, Folder 6)
        - European Community, 1992 (Box 13, Folder 7)
      - Judiciary
        - General, 1992-1994 (Box 13, Folder 8)
        - Constitutional Court, 1991-1994 (Box 13, Folder 9)
      - Jews, 1993 (Box 13, Folder 10)
      - Labor
        - General, 1993 (Box 13, Folder 11)
        - Intimidation, 1992 (Box 13, Folder 12)
        - Strikes, 1991 (Box 13, Folder 13)
      - Land, 1992-1993 (Box 13, Folder 14)
      - Laws, 1992 (Box 13, Folder 15)
      - Lustration
        - General, 1991-1993 (Box 13, Folder 16)
        - Memo on lustration, (Helsinki Watch criticism), 1993 (Box 13, Folder 17)
      - Migration, 1993-1994 (Box 13, Folder 18)
      - Military
        - General, 1994 (Box 13, Folder 19)
        - Conscientious objectors, 1993-1994 (Box 13, Folder 20)